Basar Chowdhury

Master of Science, *Bioinformatics* https://github.com/sohail

sohail.chd0202@gmail.com +1-857-930-1243 Boston, MA, 02115

Summary

Backend Software engineer with experience in design and development of APIs and microservices on AWS. Developed APIs of data backup of cloud apps (Exchange/Google/Box) and data compliance. Cloud migration of legacy applications and data processing pipeline using Kafka, Elasticsearch and Kibana. During my first 2 years in career I was working as test engineer doing network analysis, log parsing and backend API for payment system. Currently pursuing bioinformatics, data analysis and machine learning.

Skills

Languages: Python, Java, C++ (Intermediate), Bash, R, Javascript (Intermediate), HTML/CSS/JS

Frameworks and Platforms: Flask, Tornado, Requests, asyncio, sockets, BioPython, ReactJS, Bootstrap

Tools: Docker, Redis, Kafka, Elasticsearch, AWS (EC2/R), GIT, MySQL

Skills: Design and development of data processing systems, microservices and internal frameworks and Services, AWS development, Agile and Scrum

Course work: Statistics, Differential Analysis, Advance Algorithms, RNA/DNA Sequencing(Dynamic programing)

Work Experience

Druva (Data backup and discovery / Software Engineer)

29-Jan-2017 to 10-Aug-2018

- Developed APIs for backup and storage related services (AWS EC2/)
- Developed cloudapps (Exchange mail/GDrive/Box) backup and restore APIs
- Data parsing before backup for compliance (HIPAA/PHI/Legal Hold)

Awards: Optimization of custom parser, reducing unit test execution from 4 hrs to 20 mins

GSLabs (Education and Stock Market CME / Software Engineer)

27-July-2013 to 27-July-2015

- Improved dashboard and analytics performance integrating Redis
- Cloud migration of the legacy applications (AWS, Elasticsearch, Kibana)
- Custom scheduler for running automated tests in multiple docker running in AWS

Awards: Created a custom round robin scheduler for job execution for reporting and analysis on AWS

Ubisoft (Gaming and Entertainment / Test Engineer)

27-July-2013 to 27-July-2015

- Feature improvement/testing of payment gateway integration API for in game purchases
- Internal network analysis tool for capturing multiplayer logs for PS4 development box
- Debugging and unit test cases for PS4 games ('The Crew' and 'Assassins creed black flag') in C++
- CI integration with Jenkins and deployment

Github Projects

- Space Voyager: Space simulator using OpenGL, glut, irrKlang
- Many games in Java, JavaScript and C# using XNA and NodeJs apps and

Education

1. Master of Science, *Bioinformatics*, (Northeastern University, Boston)

Aug, 2018 - Apr, 2020 Anticipated

2. Bachelor Of Engineering, *Information Technology*, (University Of Pune, Pune)

May,2009 - May,2013